Guide to the Jerry Manock Collection of Apple History ephemera M1880
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
Jerry Manock Collection of Apple History ephemera
1966-2007
M1880
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
15.0 Linear feet (6 manuscript boxes, 5 record storage boxes, 3 flat boxes, 7 map folders; 1 optical disk and 4 cassettes.)
This collection contains many blueprints, artifacts, and documentation of Manock's time both at Stanford University as an engineering student and at Apple as a product designer.
Biography
Jerrold Clifford Manock (born February 21, 1944) is an American industrial designer. He worked for Apple Computer from 1977 to 1984, contributing to housing designs for the Apple II, Apple III, and earlier compact Apple Macintosh computers. Manock is widely regarded as the "father" of the Apple Industrial Design Group. Since 1976 he is the president and principal designer of Manock Comprehensive Design, Inc., with offices in Palo Alto, California, and, after 1985, in Burlington, Vermont.
Manock attended Stanford University, where he earned his B.S. in mechanical engineering in 1966 and his M.S. in Mechanical Engineering
From 1968 to 1972 Manock worked as a product design engineer in the Microwave Division of Hewlett-Packard, Palo Alto, California. From 1972 to 1975 he was chief mechanical engineer at Telesensory Systems, Inc., of Palo Alto. He then worked as a freelance product design consultant; in late 1976 he took on Apple Computer as a client and consulted on the product design and mechanical engineering of the Apple II personal computer.
Manock joined Apple in 1979 as corporate manager of product design. Working under the direction of Steve Jobs, Manock designed the Apple III and the "Cuisinart-inspired" upright casing for the Macintosh computer, which necessitated a detached keyboard. Manock also worked on the Disk II and Disk III, and hired the design staff for the Apple Lisa office computer.
In January 1981, when Jobs became manager of the Macintosh project, he brought in Manock and Terry Oyama to design the computer housing. According to Jason O'Grady in Apple Inc., Manock was "hand-pciked" by Jef Raskin to work on the Macintosh design team. In a 1984 interview, Manock said that the initial design goal was for a computer housing with "portability", but that idea was replaced by the design goal of "minimal desk space." Manock himself contributed the idea of using icons on the outside of the machine rather than English words to make the Macintosh more international. This style was mirrored by the software team in the ROM, which used icons instead of English-language directions, such as a frowning face when the computer needed to reboot and a smiling face indicating booting. [from Wikipedia and Jerry Manock]
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by Jerry Manock to Stanford University, Special Collections in February 2012.
- Series 1: Publications/Talks/Projects
  - CES, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Apple Computer, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Apple Design Guild Info, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Computer History Museum Talk, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Apple II Keyboard Replacement, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Apple II Heat Transfer Report, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - X-Plane Flight Simulator Instructions, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Product Design Guidelines, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Apple Design Documents, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Apple Press Materials, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Apple Engineering Documents, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - JCM/Apple Design Notebook, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Abby's Books, 1991, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chrona Calendar, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Conant Custom Brass, 1998-2003 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Trimble Navigation, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - MCD Business Cards, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - MCD Website, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Solar Plots, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Land Speed Record, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Seldon H2O Tech., 2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Urn Project, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Innovation Partners, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Conant Plan, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Gas Station Plan, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Slide Copier Lawsuit, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - C 26 Reviews, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sailing, 2002-2006 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Labyrinth, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Misc. Design Plans, 1970-1999 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Misc. Design Plans, 1976-2006 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Telesensory Systems "Optacon" (1 of 3), 1969-1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Telesensory Systems "Optacon" (2 of 3), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Telesensory Systems "Optacon" (3 of 3), 1978-1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - BIB: Bill Moggridge, Roger Tallon, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Visicalc Personal Software, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Apple, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Apple Brochures, Installation Instructions, 1977-1999 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bill Dresselhaus, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Time Line, 1981-1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1982/1983 Trip to Japan, Alpine Electronics & Sony, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Mac Chassis at Cam Fran Tooling Chicago, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Soft Tooling for Mac at PTA, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Musical Christmas Card from Steve Wozniak, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Apple: Organizational, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Apple Computer Inc.: Annual Reports, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Manock at Stanford, ca. 1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Macworld, 1984; Stanford Magazine, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, Documents, etc., 1978-2007 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Apple Catalogs, MacUser, 1988-1997 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Apple Documents, 1978-2002 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Apple Documents, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Macintosh Business Plan, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Design Info Directory, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Manock Designs: includes Radiance Sundial, 1997-1999 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - M&O Conversion Kit: documents and blueprints, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Esslinger: Allied International Design, 82 79 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Apple Brochures, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous articles, brochures, publications, 1970-1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Jerry Manock photographs, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Lisa Proto Photographs, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, Apple groundbreaking, n.d. [mid 1990's] (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Photographs: Axe, Mac Yell, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Airplane slides, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous slides and negatives, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - CD: X-plane, v. 8, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Series 2: Architectural Plans/Engineering School Documents
  - Untitled diagram possibly of original Mac (Map-folder 1, Item 1)
  - Untitled Diagram (Map-folder 1, Item 2)
  - Nameplate, graphics, Apple II, sheet 2 of 3 (Map-folder 1, Item 3)
  - Product I.D. System (Map-folder 1, Item 4)
  - Chassis, Apple II (Map-folder 1, Item 5)
  - Housing, Apple II, sheet 1 of 2 (Map-folder 1, Item 6)
  - Housing, Apple II, sheet 2 of 2 (Map-folder 1, Item 7)
  - Lid, Apple II (Map-folder 1, Item 8)
  - Untitled diagram with side view of keyboard (Map-folder 1, Item 9)
  - Untitled diagram taped to blank sheet (Map-folder 1, Item 10)
  - Bicycle Layout 27 Feb 1981 (Map-folder 1, Item 11)
  - Proposal Mac PCB (Map-folder 1, Item 12)
  - Untitled diagram on yellow paper 23 Feb 1977 (Map-folder 1, Item 13)
  - Untitled diagram on white paper 23 Feb 1977 (Map-folder 1, Item 14)
  - Untitled diagram with side view of keyboard (Map-folder 1, Item 15)
  - Untitled diagram 7 March 1977 (Map-folder 1, Item 16)
  - Pushbutton, Dev. system (Map-folder 1, Item 17)
  - Chassis, Mac, sheet 1 of 2 (Map-folder 2, Item 1)
  - Chassis, Mac, sheet 2 of 2 (Map-folder 2, Item 2)
  - 9'' Monitor #01 9/8/83 (Map-folder 2, Item 3)
  - Design Guide, PCB, Mac Apple-Buss (Map-folder 2, Item 4)
  - Design Guide, PCB, Mac Apple-Buss Check Print #2 JCM copy (Map-folder 2, Item 5)
  - Apple Computer blank blueprint sheet (Map-folder 2, Item 6)
  - Untitled blueprint (Map-folder 2, Item 7)
  - Fence, Main Logic Board (Map-folder 2, Item 8)
  - Housing, Rear, sheet 1 of 5 (photocopy) (Map-folder 2, Item 9)
  - Chassis, Mac, sheet 1 of 2 (Map-folder 2, Item 10)
  - Chassis, Mac, sheet 2 of 2 (Map-folder 2, Item 11)
  - Bezel, Front Hard Tooling, sheet 1 of 3 (Map-folder 2, Item 12)
  - Bezel, Front Hard Tooling, sheet 2 of 3 (Map-folder 2, Item 13)
  - Housing, Rear, sheet 1 of 5 (Map-folder 2, Item 14)
  - Housing, Rear, sheet 2 of 5 (Map-folder 2, Item 15)
  - Housing, Rear, sheet 3 of 5 (Map-folder 2, Item 16)
  - Housing, Rear, sheet 4 of 5 (Map-folder 2, Item 17)
  - Shield, Internal Disk (Map-folder 2, Item 18)
  - Compression Spring, Mouse, 8 1/2'' x 11'' sheet (Map-folder 3, Item 1)
  - Ball, Mouse, 8 1/2'' x 11'' sheet (Map-folder 3, Item 2)
  - Retainer, Mouse (Map-folder 3, Item 3)
  - Detector Aperture, Mouse (Map-folder 3, Item 4)
  - Base, Mouse (Map-folder 3, Item 5)
  - Ribcage, Mouse, sheet 1 of 2 (Map-folder 3, Item 6)
  - Ribcage, Mouse, sheet 2 of 2 (Map-folder 3, Item 7)
  - Top cover, Mouse (Map-folder 3, Item 8)
  - Portamount labeled diagram (Map-folder 4, Item 1)
  - Untitled diagram "P. 73" (Map-folder 4, Item 2)
  - Fatigue Testing Machine, 24 Nov. 1965 (Map-folder 4, Item 3)
  - Portamount Lens-Camera Holder & Track, 14 March 1966 (Map-folder 4, Item 4)
  - Untitled drawing "Black annodize" (Map-folder 4, Item 5)
  - Untitled schematic of shoe/foot contraption, 22 April 1966 (Map-folder 4, Item 6)
  - Motor Basket Detail, 3 December 1965 (Map-folder 4, Item 7)
  - Revision A diagram, 2 Dec. 1965 (Map-folder 4, Item 8)
  - Revision B diagram, 2 Dec. 1965 (Map-folder 4, Item 9)
  - Untitled diagram 18 April 1980 (Map-folder 5, Item 1)
  - Untitled diagram 41180, 11 April 1980 (Map-folder 5, Item 2)
  - Untitled drawing of front of Mac, 25 April 1983 (Map-folder 5, Item 3)
  - PTA (soft tools), 3 Oct. 1983 (Map-folder 5, Item 4)
  - Deluxe (hard tool #1), 7 October 1983 (Map-folder 5, Item 5)
  - Design Guide - P.S., P.C.B. (component side) (Map-folder 5, Item 6)
  - Design Guidelines, Main Logic P.C.B. - component side (Map-folder 5, Item 7)
  - Insert, Security (Map-folder 5, Item 8)
  - Ort Boss Mac Bezel (photocopy) (Map-folder 5, Item 9)
  - Bezel, Front Hard Tooling, sheet 2 of 3 (photocopy) (Map-folder 5, Item 10)
  - Chassis, Casting Disk, sheet 1 of 2 (Map-folder 5, Item 11)
  - Untitled diagram, 13 Nov. 1979 (Map-folder 5, Item 12)
  - Chassis, Casting Disk, sheet 2 of 2 (Map-folder 5, Item 13)
  - Chassis, machined disk (Map-folder 5, Item 14)
  - Untitled diagram, possibly of Macintosh carrying case, 6 April 1982 (Map-folder 5, Item 15)
  - Untitled diagram, "carrying case, optional" (Map-folder 5, Item 16)
  - Untitled diagram also of carrying case (Map-folder 5, Item 17)
  - Project: Bicycle timetable, 27 March 1981 (Map-folder 6, Item 1)
  - Untitled blueprint (Map-folder 6, Item 2)
  - Untitled blueprint with attached drawing of front of Macintosh (Map-folder 6, Item 3)
  - Bicyle layout, 27 February 1981 (Map-folder 6, Item 4)
  - Top half of blueprint, "Datanetics" (Map-folder 6, Item 5)
  - Untitled diagram, 18 April 1980 (Map-folder 6, Item 6)
  - Untitled diagram (Map-folder 6, Item 7)
  - Untitled diagram, 7 June 1978 (Map-folder 6, Item 8)
  - Lower half of blueprint (Map-folder 6, Item 9)
  - Untitled diagram, 12 June 1978 (Map-folder 6, Item 10)
  - Untitled diagram: "Idea - use amp front end" (Map-folder 6, Item 11)
  - Untitled diagram, 30 June 1978 (Map-folder 6, Item 12)
  - Untitled diagram (Map-folder 6, Item 13)
  - Untitled diagram, 12 June 1978 (Map-folder 6, Item 14)
  - Untitled drawing of computer (Map-folder 6, Item 15)
  - "Possible display module" diagram, 1 February 1978 (Map-folder 6, Item 16)
  - Untitled diagram (Map-folder 6, Item 17)
  - Tracking ball/joystick diagram (Map-folder 6, Item 18)
  - Untitled diagram (Map-folder 6, Item 19)
  - Untitled diagram, 30 June 1978 (Map-folder 6, Item 20)
  - Shape study - Probe IV (Map-folder 6, Item 21)
  - Shape study - Probe IV (photocopy) (Map-folder 6, Item 22)
  - Untitled sketch of radio console with attached transparency with notes, 1 December 1966 (Map-folder 6, Item 23)
  - Automobile Probe #1 (Map-folder 6, Item 24)
  - Untitled diagram of computer (Map-folder 6, Item 25)
  - Untitled large diagram with attached post-it note (Map-folder 6, Item 26)
  - Poster board with attached drawing (Flat-box 7, Folder 1)
  - Poster board with attached drawing (Flat-box 7, Folder 2)
  - Poster board with attached drawing (Flat-box 7, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook with Apple II logo design inside Poster board with attached drawing, March 15, 1983 (Flat-box 7, Folder 4)
  - Fatigue Machine schematic (Flat-box 7, Folder 5, Item 1)
  - Untitled diagram of computer monitor (Flat-box 7, Folder 5, Item 2)
  - Center console drawing with attached overlayed transparency, 1 December 1966 (Flat-box 7, Folder 5, Item 3)
  - Untitled drawing of temperature controls with attached overlayed transparency, 1 December 1966 (Flat-box 7, Folder 5, Item 4)
  - Untitled drawing of foot and gas pedal, 6 of 6 (Flat-box 7, Folder 5, Item 5)
  - ME 116a Automobile Problem #1,2, & 3, papers in folder, 17 November 1966 (Flat-box 7, Folder 5, Item 6)
  - Audubon Jr. High School Swivel Base schematic, November 19 1958 (Flat-box 7, Folder 6, Item 1)
  - Tool Post schematic (Flat-box 7, Folder 6, Item 2)
  - Pulley and Stand diagram, 1-6-59 (Flat-box 7, Folder 6, Item 3)
  - Thrust Bearing Diagram, 12-11-58 (Flat-box 7, Folder 6, Item 4)
  - Floor Plan Dorsey High, 3-20-61 (Flat-box 7, Folder 6, Item 5)
  - Untitled diagram relating to car design, 22 November 1966 (Flat-box 7, Folder 6, Item 6)
  - Control - Steering Handle, 1 of 2 (Flat-box 7, Folder 6, Item 7)
  - Drawing of Computer Base (Flat-box 7, Folder 7, Item 1)
  - Drawing of computer base (Flat-box 7, Folder 7, Item 2)
  - Computer side view diagram affixed to sheet, 4 December 1978 (Flat-box 7, Folder 7, Item 3)
  - Transparency of Printer Icon (Flat-box 7, Folder 8, Item 1)
  - Macgeocalc printed reel, 4, 6 August 1981 (Flat-box 7, Folder 8, Item 2)
  - Apple Computer Drawing List (blank) (Flat-box 7, Folder 8, Item 3)
  - Blank Apple Computer size A sheet (Flat-box 7, Folder 8, Item 4)
  - Blank Apple Computer size B sheet (Flat-box 7, Folder 8, Item 5)
  - Red drawing of Apple computer 2/81 (Flat-box 7, Folder 8, Item 6)
  - Blue drawing of computer interior 2/81 (Flat-box 7, Folder 8, Item 7)
  - Blue drawing of computer exterior 2/81 (Flat-box 7, Folder 8, Item 8)
  - Apple Computer Inc. logo sheet with missing cutout (Flat-box 7, Folder 8, Item 9)
  - Apple Computer Inc. color logo sticker sheet with removed stickers (Flat-box 7, Folder 8, Item 10)
  - Page of alphabet practice J. Manock, Period 5 (Flat-box 7, Folder 9, Item 1)
  - Final Design-Domestic Desalinization Unit portfolio containing multiple diagrams, Jan. 2, 1963 (Flat-box 7, Folder 9, Item 2)
  - Floor plan diagram, J. Manock, Period 5 (Flat-box 7, Folder 9, Item 3)
  - Plot Plan Architectual Drafting, May 8, 1961 (Flat-box 7, Folder 9, Item 4)
  - Rotary Diffusion Still portfolio with multiple diagrams, 1-2-1963 (Flat-box 7, Folder 9, Item 5)
  - 1982 Calendar; 1983 Calendar: (meetings and events) (Flat-box 8, Folder 1)
  - Rolling Stone magazine Issue 732 April 18, 1996 (Flat-box 9, Folder 1, Item 1)
  - Rolling Stone magazine Issue 416 March 1, 1984 (Flat-box 9, Folder 1, Item 2)
  - Rolling Stone magazine Issue 416 March 1, 1984 with post-it note (duplicate) (Flat-box 9, Folder 1, Item 3)
  - San Jose Mercury News 'West' section, March 20, 1988 (Flat-box 9, Folder 1, Item 4)
  - San Jose Mercury News, "The End of Apple's Crusade" article, January 28, 1996 (Flat-box 9, Folder 1, Item 5)
  - Panoramic photograph (taped) of unknown airport (Flat-box 9, Folder 2, Item 1)
  - The Washington Free Press Business Monday section, October 24, 1988 (Flat-box 9, Folder 2, Item 2)
  - Apple Media Arts magazine Vol. 1 No. 2, Summer 1988 (Flat-box 9, Folder 2, Item 3)
  - Cardboard with affixed small multicolored Apple logo decals (Flat-box 9, Folder 3, Item 1)
  - Cardboard affixed with small gray Apple logo decals (Flat-box 9, Folder 4, Item 1)
  - Posterboard affixed with various Apple decals, Oudensha Co. Ltd. (Flat-box 9, Folder 4, Item 2)
  - Two Apple Computer Inc. stickers (Flat-box 9, Folder 4, Item 3)
  - Cardboard affixed with small yellow Apple logo decals (Flat-box 9, Folder 5, Item 1)
  - Cardboard affixed with small purple Apple logo decals (Flat-box 9, Folder 5, Item 2)
  - Cardboard affixed with small orange Apple logo decals (Flat-box 9, Folder 5, Item 3)
  - Cardboard affixed with small red Apple logo decals (Flat-box 9, Folder 5, Item 4)
  - Cardboard affixed with small green Apple logo decals (Flat-box 9, Folder 5, Item 5)
  - Chartpack Heat Resistant transfer lettering sheet of multi-colored Apple logo decals (Flat-box 9, Folder 5, Item 6)
- Series 3: Artifacts
  - Apple Light Pen studies, plastic mold, peripheral cord, heat sink, vent cover, miscellaneous port interfaces, Apple patches, paperweight, miscellaneous panels, Apple stickers, metallic Apple logos, bag of metallic Macintosh logos, manilla envelopes containing various metallic logos. (Carton 10)
  - Apple license plate, Ice Hockey skate, metallic clamp/stand, metal rod. (Carton 11)
  - Knob studies, plastic molds, 316 1/4 hard samples, special Apple foot, $100 million Apple team desk piece, Ribcage for Lisa mouse, metallic Apple II logos, on/off switch, telesensory systems, security bracket, miscellaeous plastic pieces, TSI Speech+ in cloth case, Diogenes object with attached cloth case, box containing M&O drive with circuit board and handwritten note. (Carton 12)
  - Keyboard keys, various metallic objects, olive green epoxy coating sample, taped metallic object, plastic mold taped to metal piece. (Carton 13)
  - Metallic mold pertaining to Apple II. (Carton 14)
- Series 4: Media
  - Apple Cassettes: A Guided Tour of MacWrite; A Guided Tour of MacPaint; A Guided Tour of Macintosh; A Guided Tour of MacProject. (Carton 10)
  - Miscellaneous slides (Carton 10)